June 22, 1941. Under the code name Operation Barbarossa,
Nazi Germany invades the Soviet Union, its ally in the war against Poland.
At the end of October, the cities of Minsk, Smolensk, kyiv, Odessa and Kharkiv fell,
and millions of Soviet soldiers are forced to surrender, not only because they find themselves surrounded,
but also by being deprived of supplies and reinforcements. Since the authorities
Germans consider captured Soviet soldiers a particular threat, pointing them out
not only as subhuman Slavs, but as part of the "Bolshevik threat" from the very beginning
The war against the Soviet Union included the mass killing of prisoners of war.
Some 5.7 million Red Army personnel will fall into German hands during World War II.
World, and of these, 3.3 million will have died by the end of the war. However,
While millions will die, hundreds of thousands of Soviet prisoners of war will be liberated
as auxiliaries of the German army and the SS, becoming Nazi collaborators. Of these,
Nearly 5,100 men are recruited, processed, and trained as auxiliary police guards.
at the Trawniki training camp, and its main function is to participate in the
Final Solution operations, which consist of deliberate and systematic mass murder
of European Jews. One of these guards is a man who, for his brutality, would become known as
"Ivan the Terrible". His name is Ivan Marchenko. Ivan Marchenko was born on March 2, 1911 in the
Ukrainian village of Sierhiejówka, then part of the Russian Empire.
After completing the third grade of primary school, Marchenko worked as a
coal miner in Kryvyi Rih, a major steelmaking town in present-day central Ukraine,
then part of the Soviet Union. Other statements indicate that he worked for a
time as a supervisor on river barges transporting timber along the Dnieper River.
Before the outbreak of the war, Marchenko was already the father of two children,
a boy and a girl, which he had with his wife Kateryna Krawtchenko.
World War II began on September 1, 1939 with the
invasion of Poland by Nazi Germany. Poland was involved in a war in
two fronts when the Soviet Union invaded the country from the east on 17
September. The last stand of the Polish units ended on October 6.
Less than two years later, on June 22, 1941, Nazi Germany, under the name
In the form of Operation Barbarossa, it invaded the Soviet Union, its ally in the war against Poland.
Ivan Marchenko enlisted in the Red Army infantry on May 27, 1941. However,
On July 10 of that same year, he was captured by the Germans near the town of Bila Tserkva,
about 80 km south of kyiv. Shortly after his capture, his third son was born.
After his internment in a prisoner of war camp in Ukraine, Marchenko was transferred
to Stalag 319, a prisoner of war camp located in the city of Chełm,
in German-occupied eastern Poland. It is estimated that around 200,000 prisoners
war soldiers passed through this camp, of whom about 90,000 died. However,
Ivan Marchenko was not one of them. In October 1941, he was selected for the Trawniki camp.
where the Nazis trained prisoners of war to work as guards
of the SS in Operation Reinhardt, the code name for the German plan to
murder the approximately two million Jews living in occupied Poland.
Between September 1941 and September 1942, SS and police officers recruited,
processed and trained 2,500 auxiliary police guards,
known as Trawniki men, at the Trawniki training camp, located about 40
kilometers southeast of Lublin, in German-occupied Poland. Virtually all of them
had been Soviet prisoners of war. The deployment in the "Solution" operations
"Final" —which consisted of the mass murder of the Jews of Europe— became the function
key to the guards trained by Trawniki. Trawniki men provided the units
on duty at the Reinhard Operation killing centers in Bełżec, Sobibor, and Treblinka.
The SS and German police authorities deployed the Trawniki men in the
Deportation operations from large and small ghettos in German-occupied Poland,
as well as escorts for transport trains from the ghettos to the extermination centers.
Among the ghettos where Trawniki-trained guards were deployed, there were also
were Warsaw, Lublin and Krakow. In February 1942, Ivan Marchenko was
gathering Jews in Lublin to send them to the extermination camps.
In May of that same year, Marchenko was sent to the Treblinka extermination camp,
built in the summer of 1942. It was the third extermination center,
after Bełżec and Sobibor, established by the authorities of Operation Reinhard.
At Treblinka, the Germans would compete with the Trawniki guards in brutality.
towards the people selected to die. In each gas chamber there were five or six Germans,
In addition to the drivers with their dogs. Drivers like Ivan Marchenko were the
Trawniki guards who operated the gas chambers, built next to the engine room,
equipped with several engines taken from large trucks and tanks. When the guards
Trawniki started the engine, the exhaust gases were piped to the gas chambers,
thus killing the people inside. Although at first the Nazis
They claimed to be able to "process" (i.e., "kill") a train of about 3,000
people in about three hours, later reducing it to about 30 minutes. In one hour,
The gas chambers were opened and the bodies were taken out, stripped and burned in a
structure made of railroad tracks that served as an open-air crematorium.
Because of the special ferocity that Marchenko exhibited when dealing with the
Jews during the massacre, quickly earned the nickname "Ivan Grozny",
which in Polish means "Ivan the Terrible". His former comrade, Nikolay Shalayev,
He described him like this: "Tall, with black hair, hazel eyes, thin and rectangular face,
large, thin, straight nose; a barely visible oblique scar; robust build; broad shoulders;
When walking, his arms were not straight, but half bent at the elbows." In the countryside,
Marchenko wore a black uniform similar to that of the German SS and often also wore
a leather jacket. Armed with a pistol, he always wandered around the countryside wielding one
a two-meter-long water pipe and a whip. Marchenko was a friend of the camp's deputy commandant,
Kurt Franz, and he always hung out with the German guards, especially with the SS-Oberscharführer
Fritz Schmidt, head of the SS workshop and the metalworks workshop. Marchenko and Schmidt
They repaired cars together, and when the transports arrived, they were usually together on the ramp.
As a motorcyclist, Marchenko not only started the engine, but also whipped the condemned prisoners.
to death, shouting: "Quick, quick, the water is going to get cold, others still have to shower!"
Sometimes, when those condemned to death approached the gas chambers, they would retreat in terror,
trying to reverse their steps. At that time, whips were used,
batons and even iron bars. Once inside, Marchenko made sure that the door of each
chamber was locked before the next one began to be filled. Once
The chambers on both sides of the hall were filled by Marchenko and his aforementioned comrade Shalayev.
They went together to the engine room and started the engines to begin the suffocation process.
With the engine running, Marchenko looked out a window to see how the process was progressing.
former comrade Vladimirovich Leleko later recalled that, when he asked Marchenko
who was looking out the window, replied: "I see people writhing, writhing."
Marchenko was an expert at killing people with his two-meter-long water pipe. After
of the war, his former comrade testified how Marchenko, with a single hit of the pipe,
killed a physically strong man. Ivan Marchenko was also a sexual deviant.
With his sword, he stabbed women's thighs and genitals on the way to the gas chambers and,
Sometimes he even raped them. He often used his gun to
cutting off women's breasts, as well as their noses and ears. The ears
He would then nail them to the walls. He also used to gouge out his victims' eyes.
In Treblinka, Ivan the Terrible had a dog that tore off parts of the human body afterward.
upon receiving the order. Marchenko called this animal, trained to cut off genitals,
and pointed at someone. Then the dog would tear out the sexual organ,
and blood was spilling everywhere.
Epstein later testified: "Ivan particularly enjoyed stabbing
pregnant women with a sword and splitting skulls with an iron pipe. He was insatiable. A
One day, a girl between 12 and 14 years old came out of the gas chamber alive sobbing: "I want my mother."
Ivan approached one of the Jewish workers and ordered him to rape her. The worker refused,
So he and the girl were taken to a mass grave and shot.
On another occasion, Marchenko was seen snatching a baby from a naked woman before she
entered a gas chamber and smashed his skull against the wall. On another occasion,
stabbed a woman and her child with an axe. Ivan Marchenko was an alcoholic who always
He was drunk, both on and off the field. On one occasion, outside the complex,
He attacked one of his comrades, named Fyodor Ryabeka, who later recalled:
'I was in the village of Wólka Okrąglik and met Marchenko, who hit me with
the fist. He was very drunk and the next day he said he didn't remember what had happened.
By the time the Treblinka extermination camp was dismantled in the
By the autumn of 1943, the camp staff had murdered approximately 925,000 Jews,
as well as an unknown number of Poles, Roma, and Soviet prisoners of war.
All traces of the camp's existence were destroyed. Lupins were planted on the land and a
on the property to a farmer of German ethnicity to camouflage the reality of what happened there.
On September 20, 1943, a convoy of SS men and about 100 Ukrainian guards from the
extermination camps of Operation Reinhardt left Lublin for the port city
From Trieste, on the Adriatic coast of northeastern Italy. Ivan Marchenko and Nikolay Shalayev
were part of the convoy. In Trieste, Marchenko was wearing an SS uniform and,
Armed with a rifle, he guarded the prison of Trieste and participated in
the roundup of Italian citizens for forced labor in Germany.
In 1944, as the Allied forces approached, Marchenko and a driver named
Gregory fled in an armored vehicle to the partisans in Yugoslavia.
After the war, Marchenko's former comrade, Nikolay Shalayev, recalled their last meeting
saying the following: "At the end of March 1945, I saw Marchenko leaving a brothel. In
At that time, he was no longer serving with the Germans, but with the partisans and, he said, he had come from
permission. He invited me to a nearby restaurant where he began to tell me about his escape from the Germans.
Marchenko told me that he had no intention of returning home at the end of the war and that he wanted to stay
in Fiume, where he had a Yugoslavian girlfriend whom he wanted to marry and who wanted to settle there.
This girl was involved with the partisans and received information from them about the Germans.
Marchenko was never heard from again, and ultimately, he never faced justice for his crimes.
During the 1970s and 1980s, John Demjanjuk, a retired auto worker
of Ukrainian descent from the Cleveland suburbs, was accused of being Ivan the Terrible.
He was tried in Israel in 1988 and sentenced to death, but the conviction was overturned after
that Soviet archives identified Ivan Marchenko as Ivan the Terrible, which led to the
Israel's Supreme Court acquitted Demjanjuk in 1993 on the grounds of reasonable doubt. In addition, 31 former guards
Ukrainians from Treblinka claimed that Marchenko looked different from the accused.
No tears were shed for Ivan Marchenko. Thank you for watching World History Channel. Don't forget.
Like, subscribe, and click the notification bell.
Don't miss our next videos, thanks, see you next time on the channel.